Henry C. Hart Correspondence, 1864-1872
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Henry C. Hart Correspondence, 1864-1872
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
18
1 box (0.25 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry (Hank) C. Hart served in Company H, 204th Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers. His cousin, John C. Hart, was stationed at the Camp of the 100 P.E.E. in Petersburg, Virginia. Henry wrote to his parents who apparently were named John and Mary Nixon and who lived in Ohioville, Beaver County, Pennsylvania. The discrepancy in the last names is unexplained by the letters.
Scope and Content
Most of these papers are letters from Henry C. Hart to his parents, John and Mary Nixon, who also received two letters from their nephew, John C. Hart. The letters relate to camp life in a number of Northern Virginia and Washington, D.C. locations: Soldiers Rest, Alexandria; Camp or Fort Reynolds, D.C.; Fort Sumner, D.C.; Rectortown, Fauquier County; Vienna, Virginia; Flint Hill, Rappahannock County; and Fairfax Station. Henry writes about breaking colts for the army, his health, wounded comrades, and his needs for food, clothes, boots, writing paper and stamps. He describes his delight at seeing Washington for the first time.
There are also letters to the Nixons from Thompson Todd, and a bill for a list of merchandise to John Nixon from A.Y. Montgomery.
Arrangement
Henry C. Hart's letters are in chronological order and foldered by location. John C. Hart's, Thompson Todd's, and miscellaneous papers are at the end.
Index Terms
Hart, Henry C.; Hart, John C.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives
Contents List
- Henry C. Hart, Fort Reynolds, September 6, 1864; November 15, 1864 (Box-folder 18:1)
- Henry C. Hart, Fort Sumner, September 19, 1864 (Box-folder 18:2)
- Henry C. Hart, Soldiers Rest, October 20, 1864 (Box-folder 18:3)
- Henry C. Hart, Rectortown, October 25 and 28, 1864 (Box-folder 18:4)
- Henry C. Hart, Vienna, Virginia, December 13, 1864; March 23, 1865; April 4 and 14, 1865 (Box-folder 18:5)
- Henry C. Hart, Flint Hill, February 15, 22, and 27, 1865; May 24, 1865 (Box-folder 18:6)
- Henry C. Hart, Fairfax Station, June 19, 1865 (Box-folder 18:7)
- Henry C. Hart, Smith's Ferry, Pennsylvania, April 24, [1865?] (Box-folder 18:8)
- Miscellaneous envelopes, letters, bill, 1865-1870 (Box-folder 18:9)
- Thompson Todd and Caroline Todd to John and Mary Nixon, June 15, 1860-February 6, 1872 (Box-folder 18:10)
- John C. Hart, Camp of the 100 Petersburg, November 4, 1864; December 1, 1864 (Box-folder 18:11)